Guide to the Spy Hop Productions independent film collection 2000-2009
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
- Mohammed raw footage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 90)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake", 2003 (Video 1)
    Mohammed talks about his difficulty coming to an American school.
    Mohammed talks about his involvement in sports at Highland High School.
    Various shots of Highland High School field.
    Exterior shot, African Grocery Store.
    Mohammed talks to people in the African Grocery Store.
    Mohammed and his family gather for a large feast/celebration (various shots of the food and people decorating a hall before hand).
    Mohammed shows the cameraperson three statuettes from Egypt.
    Walking towards the camera, Mohammed introduces himself.
    A young American girl interviews Mohammed about what he thought about the US before and after he moved to America.
    Mohammed and his cousin dance in front of the camera.
    Voice over, Mohammed tells the story of his grandfather (first president of Somalia) and why their family had to flee the country.
- Mohammed raw footage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 91)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake", 2003 (Video 1)
    Interior Highland High School, hallway.
    Mohammed and friends walk down a flight of stairs.
    Statue of the Highland High School Ram.
    Highland High School Cafeteria.
    Highland High School Gym. Mohammed plays ball with friends.
    Highland High School track. Mohammed and his friends run around the track in a casual race as others look on.
    Mohammed and other students work in a computer lab.
    Highland High School hall, Mohammed and friends walk down hall.
    Interior, Highland High School, stairwell.
    Girls walk down a hall.
    Students converse in hallway between class periods.
- Mohammed raw footage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 92)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    Interview with a young man, Abdul Karilm Aden, about life as a refugee in Utah, negative experiences with racial hatred from other minorities, etc.
    Interview with a young man, Ismael Ruzi, about life as a refugee in Utah, the importance of education, racial tension, and plans for the future.
    Interview with a young woman, Nima Yusef, about life as Somalian refugee in Utah, culture clashes, and religion.
    Interview with two young women on an outside bench about life as a refugee in Utah, dating, and gossips.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 93)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    A group of ESL high school boys from Highland High School talk as a man teaches a girl how to use the camera.
    Interview with a classroom full of ESL high school students from Highland High School about problems with their American peers and members of the community.
    Interview with a young woman, Nima Yusef, from Highland High School about life as a Somalian refugee in Salt Lake.
    ESL students gather around a camera as a woman explains how to use it properly and connect it to the tripod.
    A young woman working the camera, talks to fellow students in the hall.
    Students brainstorm about what they will film for their film (i.e. holidays, celebrations, activities, etc.)
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 94)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    Teens from Highland High School compete in an obstacle course in the gym.
    Two teens dressed in sumo wrestler costumes wrestle.
    Students in the stands of the Highland High School gym watch as two teens dressed in sumo wrestler costumes wrestle.
    Different classes (i.e. Sophomores, Seniors) yell spirit cheers to each other in the gym of Highland High School.
    Teens compete in an orange pass and other relay events in the Highland High School gym.
    ESL students sit in the stands in the Highland High School gym.
    Two teams (girls) play "Tug of War".
    Two teams (boys) play "Tug of War".
    Various shots of the crowd.
    Various groups perform dances for the crowd.
    Panel discussion with ESL students to members of the Highland High School student body. (sound corrupted, low levels)
    Interview with Kevin Smith, a teacher at Highland High School who works with refugee students there.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 95)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    Int. Mosque - women and children on the upper floor converse as men on the lower floor kneel and listen to chanting.
    Nima Yusef prays during a service at Mosque
    Int. Mosque - women and children on the upper floor converse
    Ext. Mosque - Families converse on the grounds as children play around the snowy area
    Interview with Eleanor Ridalgi, an teen immigrant from north Africa attending Highland High School, about Valentine's Day and the difference between American culture and that of her home country.
    Interview with a seventeen-year-old refugee from Afghanistan attending Highland High School about his experience coming to and adjusting to life in the United States and Utah in particular.
    A young man plays around with the microphone.
    Practice interview with Ken Powell to prepare the Spy Hop group for their interview with Mayor Rocky Anderson (mayor of Salt Lake City), who has worked with and knows several refugees and their families in the Salt Lake City area.
    Interview with Ken Powell about working with refugee students. (sound corrupted, low levels)
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 96)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    Interview with Nima Yusef, a teen refugee from Somalia living in Salt Lake City and attending Highland High School.
    Ext. Salt Lake City street, day. A group of refugee girls walk on a sidewalk and wait for their bus to school until others join them.
    Refugee students ride the bus to school at Highland High School.
    Refugee students exit bus and walk towards Highland High School.
    Int. Highland High School cafeteria, day. Refugee students sit a table and converse.
    Ext. Highland High School, day.
    Interview with Jared Allen (?) about the definition of a refugee.
    Interview with Chad Beckham about the definition of a refugee.
    Interview with a young woman about the definition of a refugee.
    Interview with a young refugee woman in a yellow sari from Somalia attending Highland High School about her experience as a refugee in Utah.
    Interview with a young refugee woman from Somalia attending Highland High School about her experience as a refugee in Utah.
    Interview with a young refugee woman from Somalia, Nima Yusef, attending Highland High School about her experience as a refugee in Utah.
    Voice over narration, story about Nima Sien (?), a Somalian refugee living in Utah.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 97)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    A Highland High School refugee student poses for the camera.
    Students work on a laptop computer.
    A Highland High School refugee student, Nima Yusef, talks to other students as she stands at the front of the room. (sound corrupted, no sound)
    Highland High School refugee students practice a traditional African dance on stage.
    A large group of Highland High School refugee students practice a dance on stage.
    Nima Yusef sits in a chair beating a traditional Somalian drum while wearing traditional clothes. (sound corrupted, no sound)
    View of I-15 or I-80 from a moving vehicle.
    Nima Yusef sits in a chair wearing traditional clothes. (sound corrupted, no sound)
    Traditional Somalian food on display.
    Still pictures of Highland High School refugee students.
    Interview with a Highland High School refugee student about the history of the ESL program at the school.
    Interview with Nima Yusef, about her hopes for the future after high school.
    A Highland High School refugee student laughs with another young woman.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 98)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    Highland High School track meet.
    A Highland High School student sits in a kitchen area and talks to the camera about his experience as a member of the track team for the school.
    A group of refugee teens from Highland High School eat and discuss traditional Somalian foods.
    A woman wearing traditional Somalian dress sits on a couch and talks to the camera in her native language before reading to Koran aloud.
    A young boy talks to the camera from the same living room as the Somalian woman who read from the Koran.
    A young woman reclines on the couch as the boy can be heard off screen.
    Close up of GPA Improvement Award from Highland High School for Ismail Hussein.
    Pictures and various items on a push pin corkboard.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 99)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    Refugee panel discussion at Highland High School with the student body (filmed from the right of the stage).
    Refugee panel discussion at Highland High School with the student body. (sound corrupted, partial sound, low levels at times)
- "Let Me Be Heard" raw footage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 100)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop Documentary "Let Me Be Heard", 2003 (Video 1)
    Interview with a young man, Paki Vahe, who grew up in both Tonga and Salt Lake City about his impressions and opinions about the Salt Lake area and difficulties he had acclimating to US and Utah culture.
    Paki Vahe performs on a song he composed on the keyboard.
    A young man sits at a keyboard as a young woman (off camera) sings an accompaniment for a track.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 101)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    Men and boys worship at a Salt Lake City mosque.
    A man preaches about the lessons of Mohammed the prophet to a room full of men and boys.
    A man in a white traditional gown bids the parishioners to donate money to the mosque and its charities.
    A man in a traditional gray gown speaks to the parishioners about the Koran.
    Mohammed (a refugee from Somalia attending Highland High School) Stands in the room with other men.
    Various shots of men in the mosque.
    A man sings from the Koran.
    Mohammed talks with his friends as men from the mosque converse after prayer.
    Highland High School ESL students talk in a classroom.
    Mohammed talks to the camera about assimilating into American culture.
    Edward (a Highland High School ESL student and Sudanese refugee) talks about his hobbies such as playing soccer.
    Mohammed interviews a soccer coach for the students about issues they face playing soccer in American and how the team can help the refugee students adjust and make friends.
    Various shots of a soccer game between a team in black and white (Highland High School) and one in red uniforms.
    A young man looks through a Spanish dictionary as he sits in the ESL classroom.
    A young Somalian woman gives an oral report to the class.
    Edward presents an oral report to the class.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 102)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    Various shots of ESL students and classroom. (sound corrupted, partial sound)
    Ext. long shot, Highland High School north side.
    Various shots of ESL students on Highland High School grounds, day. (sound corrupted, low levels)
    Highland Rams sign.
    Students in P.E. clothes play with a soccer ball on the field.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 103)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    A group of Highland High School refugee students prepare a camera for an interview with Salt Lake City Mayor, Rocky Anderson.
    Interview with Salt Lake City Mayor, Rocky Anderson. (Image and sound corruption, blurry, low audio levels)
    Various shots of camera crew and students as crew prepares for an interview with Highland High School student body president.
    Various shots of students in a classroom. (sound corrupted, low levels)
    Interview with Highland High School student body president.
    Side-view, interview with a teacher. (sound corrupted, low levels)
    Various shots of ESL students in a classroom as the students discuss what to show in the documentary they plan to film.
    Side-view, interview with a teacher/coach. (sound corrupted, low levels)
    Track practice for Highland High School.
    Shot of Nima Yusef as she sits in a desk chair and talks to people off camera.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 104)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    An ESL student in a blue plaid dress shirt holds up a red paper to cover his face from the camera before finally lowering it and talking to the person behind the camera about assimilating to US culture after he left his home country.
    An instructor films several of the students and asks them various questions about living the US after fleeing their homelands.
    Highland High School Student Body President addresses the student body and announces a girl who sung the national anthem.
    A group of ESL girls perform a traditional Somalian dance on stage for the student body.
    A group of three ESL girls perform a traditional middle-eastern (Armenian?) dance for the student body.
    Three teen boys perform a song by their band for the student body as well as "What I Got" by Sublime.
    A presentation of a plaque.
    A large group of young men present a Polynesian "slap dance".
    A group of teen girls dressed in khakis and white tank tops perform a dance.
    A group of teen girls dressed in sports jerseys perform a dance.
    A group of girls and boys perform a cheerleader-like dance as the student body sings their alma mater song.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 105)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    ESL students converse in the Highland High School Library.
    ESL student gets books at her locker.
    Two ESL students wait at a bus stop bench.
    ESL students wait for the 30 UTA bus westbound and ride it home.
    Stills and footage of one of the ESL students and her home and family.
    An ESL student films another as they walk the grounds of the Salt Lake County Government Center.
    Footage of one of the ESL students and her home and family.
    ESL students enjoy lunch in the Highland High School cafeteria.
    ESL students from Highland High School mingle in a school hallway.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 106)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    Interview with Salt Lake City Mayor, Rocky Anderson about refugees living in the Salt Lake area, assistance programs for housing, education, and employment, and the refugee contributions to the city.
    Interview with the Highland High School student body president about the school's considerations for refugee students, its programs, and how to better include them in the activities of the school. Also, the difficulty of being a sort of governing liaison between the refugee and "mainstream" students.
    Interview with Highland High School teacher, Mrs. Horch, working with the ESL program at the school as she recaps some of the history and progress of the program. (sound corrupted, partial sound)
    Interview with Jason R. Thomas, a teacher at Highland High School who works with refugee students there. Thomas admits that one of the things he enjoys most about working with refugee students is their desire to learn and do new things although it may be a challenge.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 107)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    A Somalian refugee student talks to the camera person and does a dance in a Highland High School hall.
    Mohammed, a Somalian refugee student from Highland High School, talks to the camera person as he shows off his house and dances in his bedroom.
    Interview with Mohammed about going to Highland High School and what he enjoys about his life in the United States. (sound corrupted, low levels)
    Mohammed and three other young men play basketball in a church or community center gymnasium.
    Two young men have a "rap-off". (sound corrupted, low levels)
    A young boy talks to the camera. (Image corruption, poor exposure)
    A young man (camera operator) walks through a house inhabited by several people as they watch television and lounge before then moving out doors in his apartment complex.
    Edward, a Somalian refugee student from Highland High School, stands in the ESL classroom at Highland High School as he rap-talks to the camera.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 108)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    A young man wearing a blue and white striped t-shirt speaks to the camera in a foreign language (Somali?).
    A young man wearing a black, long-sleeved t-shirt (Ahmed) speaks to the camera in a foreign language (Somali?).
    Mohammed speaks to the camera in a foreign language (Somali?).
    Mohammed and the boys in the blue and white striped t-shirt enter a downstairs den as rap music plays on a stereo. The boy in the striped t-shirt (Ahmed) gives a tour of the room and other parts of the house.
    Stills of Mohammed spotting one of the boys as he lifts weights.
    The boy in the long-sleeved t-shirt (Ahmed) serves as the cameraperson as they all mess around in the downstairs den playing cards, joking and laughing in a foreign language (Somali?).
    One of the young men from the den drives a car, footage from a moving vehicle of Salt Lake City residential area (possibly Sugarhouse).
    Interview with Mohammed about when and why his family left Somalia and then Egypt and how they came to reside in Salt Lake City.
    Mohammed works the camera as he speaks with young men and women in a house in another language (Somali?).
    Young man in black, long-sleeved t-shirt (Ahmed) talks to camera and he and two other teen pose as someone takes their picture.
    A group of teens and a mother walk into a house, night.
    Three teen boys play video games.
    Mohammed films several items such as photographs in a house.
    The two young men accompanying Mohammed talk to the camera on a UTA bus.
    Ahmed points to his school, East High School from the bus.
    A young man talks to the camera as Ahmed films.
    Mohammed talks to the camera about playing sports such as basketball and football.
    Mohammed sits on a couch with another young man and they talk to each other. (sound corrupted, low levels)
    Mohammed writes in Arabic in a notebook.
    Mohammed, dressed in a traditional Somalian garment and a western dress-shirt, talks to the camera about his clothing. (sound corrupted, low levels)
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 109)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    Refugee panel discussion at Highland High School with the student body (filmed from slightly left of the stage). Discussion about what the students miss about their home countries, where they are from and how long they have been in the United States. Also discussed are issues pertaining to being refugee students at Highland High School.
- Refugee documentary projects raw rootage, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 110)
  - Raw footage for Spy Hop documentary "From Somalia to Salt Lake" also possibly used for "Dream Come True?" involving teen refugees living in Salt Lake, 2003 (Video 1)
    Edward, an ESL refugee student at Highland High School, talks to the camera
    Tail-end of "Dream Come True?" with closing statement and credits (see item 7)
    Ahmed, (see item 109) talks to the camera as he holds it and spins around in a desk chair.
    A young man talks to the camera about why his mother chose to come to the US with him.
    Interview with the Highland High School student body president (see item 107).
    Short statement from the interview with a Highland High School teacher, Mr. Jason Thomas (see item 107).
    Four teen ESL students walk down a street as a bus drives by.
    "Special Thanks To" credits for "Dream Come True?" (see item 7).
    An ESL teen girl student walks down a front door walkway to the sidewalk.
    Various ESL students present their "Personal Presentations" in front of the camera as the other students look on and comment about what they want to talk about in the documentary they plan to make.